<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2017 Goldman Sachs.
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.

-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Command-line API</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <p>
        The command line format is generally as follows:
        <source>$OBEVO_PATH/bin/deploy.sh &lt;COMMAND&gt; -arg1 arg -arg2 arg etc</source>
        where &lt;COMMAND&gt; is one of the following:
        </p>

        <macro name="toc">
            <param name="fromDepth" value="0" />
            <param name="toDepth" value="1" />
        </macro>

        <section name="DEPLOY">
            <p>This is the main command for Obevo that will deploy your source changes to your target environment.
            It will  1) read your source changes  2) read the changes already deployed in the audit table  3) calculate
            the difference  4) deploy the changes</p>

            <p>Arguments:</p>

            -sourcePath &lt;arg&gt;
            <ul>
                <li>The path to your DB source path (i.e. the directory where your system config file resides, or the direct path to the system config file itself</li>
                <li>Required</li>
            </ul>

            -action &lt;arg&gt;
            <ul>
                <li>2 possible arguments:
                    <ul>
                        <li>clean - wipes away all objects from the schemas defined in your config. Useful for dev and test environments</li>
                        <li>deploy - does a standard deploy</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>You can specify as a comma-separated list if you want to do multiple commands</li>
                <li>Optional - defaults to deploy</li>
            </ul>

            -env &lt;arg&gt;
            <ul>
                <li>The environment name/s defined in your config that you want to deploy. You can specify a comma-separated list or a wildcard via * or % (i.e. dev0*, %prod)</li>
                <li>Optional if the config at your source path only defines 1 environment, then that is chosen. Otherwise, this is required.</li>
            </ul>

            Credentials: -deployUserId &lt;arg&gt;, -password &lt;arg&gt;, -useKerberosAuth
            <ul>
                <li>Either provide deployUserId + password, or deployUserId + useKerberos if you kinit beforehand and the platform supports it</li>
                <li>Optional: if not provided at command line or from config, you will be prompted</li>
            </ul>

            -noPrompt
            <ul>
                <li>Defines if the deployment will proceed without any user interaction or prompting</li>
                <li>Optional - defaults to false (i.e. users are prompted by default)</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="PREVIEW">
            <p>PREVIEW is a read-only mode command that will show the user the changes that expect to be deployed (i.e.
                the first 3 steps mentioned in the DEPLOY command), but it will not actually deploy the changes.</p>
            <p>This is a convenience for teams that just want to see the changes that will get deployed using a read-only db id</p>

            Same args as DEPLOY are used, except for -action
        </section>
        <section name="INIT">
            <p>The INIT command is used when onboarding an existing system to Obevo to mark your initial schema as "already deployed" in the system.</p>

            <p>See the <a href="onboarding-guide.html">Onboarding Guide</a> for details.</p>

            <p>Essentially, this will execute a DEPLOY command, just without executing your source code to the DB - it will just update the deploy audit table.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="Reverse Engineering Commands">
            <p>These commands are used when you need to onboard an existing system to Obevo.</p>

            <p>They would extract the DB schema from your existing data and put it into the Obevo file format.</p>

            <p>See the <a href="onboarding-guide.html">Onboarding Guide</a> for details.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>