<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2017 Goldman Sachs.
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.

-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>DB Project Best Practices</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="DB Project Best Practices">
            <macro name="toc">
                <param name="fromDepth" value="2" />
                <param name="toDepth" value="3" />
            </macro>

            <h3>Logical schema name should match production or otherwise be environment-agnostic</h3>

            <p>The logical schema name should be representative of your schema across environments. When onboarding an
                existing schema, this typically means to match it to production (though not always)
            </p>

            <p>In observing some teams onboarding, we see a habit of naming the logical schema in the &lt;schemas&gt;
                section in the system-config.xml file as the name of the dev schema that is being deployed to. This is not
                correct - it is preferred to match it to prod, and then to leverage the dbSchemaPrefix/Suffix or
                schemaOverrides to map it to the dev schema.
            </p>

            <p>We will improve the reverse-engineering support in the future to also generate a template system-config.xml
                file for you as to avoid confusion on this in the future.
            </p>

            <h3>Table //// CHANGEs should be as fine-grained as reasonable to ease recoverability</h3>

            <p>See the "Transactionality Considerations" section in the
                <a href="error-handling.html">Error Handling page</a>
                for
                details
            </p>


            <h3>Set up a dedicated test schema to run a deploy against in your continuous builds</h3>

            <p>If you commit code, you should have automated tests for it; that applies not just to your application code,
                but to your database code.
            </p>

            <p>At minimum, you should be able to validate the correctness of the SQL you deployed. The best way to do this
                is to simply deploy your schema to an environment! This requires an actual environment to test against, esp.
                for DBMS platforms whose specific SQL dialects and storage settings cannot be tested against an in-memory double.
            </p>


            <h3>Do not include references to the same schema in your DDLs</h3>

            <p>e.g. If your objects are for schmea MYSCHEMA1, then do not qualify your object references with the schema, e.g.
                <source><![CDATA[CREATE TABLE MYSCHEMA1.TAB1 (  -- Not OK

CREATE TABLE TAB1 (  -- OK]]></source>
            </p>

            <p>This is so that you have flexibility in deploying your objects to differently named schemas (whether suffixed
                differently like MYSCHEMA1_QA or to reuse objects in other projects)
            </p>

            <p>The reverse-engineering steps should already take care of removing the object qualifiers from the same schema.
                But if somehow the qualifiers are not removed, then please do so manually.
            </p>

            <h3>Tokenize references to other schemas in your objects</h3>

            <p>Take a view defined in MYSCHEMA1 that refers to another schema OTHERSCHEMA1, like so:</p>

            <source><![CDATA[CREATE VIEW MYVIEW1 AS SELECT * FROM OTHERSCHEMA1.OTHER_TABLE]]></source>

            <p>Per the point above, we'd like to have flexibility in the schema to deploy to.</p>

            <p>You can define tokens yourself (see the<a
                href="environment-management.html">tokenization doc</a>), or you
                can use the built-in tokens for the physical schema name. For example, assuming you've defined the logical schema
                name as THATSCHEMA in your system-config.xml that maps to the OTHERSCHEMA1 physical schema, use the token as
                below (&lt;logicalSchema&gt;_physicalSchema)
            </p>

            <source><![CDATA[CREATE VIEW MYVIEW1 AS SELECT * FROM ${THATSCHEMA_physicalName}.OTHER_TABLE]]></source>

            <h3>Consider leveraging the in-memory DB translation feature for unit testing your DB access code</h3>

            <p>While unit test databases cannot test the exact SQL syntax that you define, they can prove useful for testing
                your application code that needs to access the DB, e.g. your ORM layer or your data-access code. Hopefully your
                code is agnostic to the underlying DBMS technology, esp. if you are using an ORM or ANSI SQL.
            </p>

            <p>To help create an in-memory DB from your DDLs without having to resort to a separate copy just for the
                in-memory DB, try out the<a href="in-memory-db-testing.html">in-memory DB conversion feature</a>.
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>e.g. if you use Hibernate's schema generation from the POJOs, it would be a better idea to move to
                    Obevo's instead
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>