<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2017 Goldman Sachs.
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.

-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Developer Guide</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <macro name="toc">
            <param name="fromDepth" value="0" />
            <param name="toDepth" value="1" />
        </macro>

        <section name="Quick Code Walkthrough + Key Classes:">
            First, read through these:
            <ol>
                <li>
                    <a href="design-walkthrough.html">Design Walkthrough</a>
                    to understand what the tool is trying to do and how
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="java-api.html">Java API</a>
                    to see the module structure and understand the tool from a client perspective
                </li>
            </ol>

            Pay special attention to the "Developer Guide note" mentions in the Design Walkthrough to see how the design maps to the code.
        </section>

        <section name="Getting started with coding">
            <p>Try out any of the unit tests and ITs in the DBMS-specific modules or the scenario test modules.</p>
            <p>These will typically invoke deployments against actual DBs and vet that the results in the DB are correct</p>
            <p>You can use these to see the full code path executed and trace through as you need to</p>
        </section>

        <section name="Adding a new DBMS implementation">
            <h4>1. Create and setup a blank DB schema to run your tests against</h4>
            <p>Obevo will run tests against actual DBMSs that have schemas dedicated to Obevo.</p>
            <p>Get a schema to facilitate your testing</p>
            <h4>2. Create a new module obevo-db-&lt;dbmsName&gt;</h4>
            <p>You can use obevo-db-db2 or obevo-db-postgresql as examples</p>
            <h4>3. Implement the classes required to do a basic incremental deployment for simple objects like tables
            </h4>
            <p>These classes revolve around setting up the JDBC parameters and such:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>AppContext, DbType, Dialect, DataSourceFactory, and SqlExecutor implementations (refer to the
                    example
                    for the exact names)
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>Also implement a DbMetadataDialect for your new implementation in obevo-schemacrawler</p>
            <p>Start w/ tables for now; we will get to stored procedures/views/etc. later</p>
            <h4>4. Implement an integration test in your module</h4>
            <p>Follow the examples, e.g. PostgreSqlDeployerIT</p>
            <p>Most examples will have a &quot;step1&quot; and &quot;step2&quot; - the idea is to do the initial
                deployment
                and then a subsequent update so that you can vet both cases
            </p>
            <h4>5. Add support for the other DB Object types, e.g. stored procedures, views, static data</h4>
            <p>etc.</p>
            <h4>6. Add the -cleanFirst command to your test to vet out the cleaning command</h4>
            <p>Note that some of the DBMS types require specific sqls to query out the db objects that schemacrawler
                cannot
                get to. This would be declared in the *AppContext class if applicable
            </p>
            <h4>7. Add reverse-engineering support</h4>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Run the steps in the user guide for reverse-engineering from Aqua</li>
                <li>Try the AquaRevengTest for your module to ensure that the code can get formatted into the right
                    structure
                </li>
                <li>Modify the code as needed to get it to work (most of the work is just in parsing the text for the
                    object
                    names, and at this point, hopefully should not require much changes at this point for new DBMS's)
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>