<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2017 Goldman Sachs.
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.

-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Obevo</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Welcome">
        Welcome to the Obevo Home Page. This tool and most of this wiki focuses on Database Deployment
        </section>
        <section name="Feature List">
            <ul>
                <li>Organized maintenance of all your DB-object files (tables, stored procedures, views, static data)
                    <ul>
                        <li>1 file per object - just as you would with Java files</li>
                        <li>Edit stored procedures, views, and static data files in place (if you have them) - just as you would with Java files</li>
                        <li>No need to specify the order in which to deploy your files - Obevo figures it out for you (a la a Java compiler compiling classes)</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>

                <li>Deploys to DB2, Sybase ASE, Sybase IQ</li>
                <li>In-memory DB support - convert your scripts to an in-memory database for unit testing support</li>
                <li>Easy onboarding - get your production schema checked in and deployed to other environments in under 2 hours</li>
                <li>Runnable from Java, command-line, or maven</li>
                <li>Easy integration into your SDLC and deployment - package and deploy alongside your Java code and run a simple command like this:</li>
                <li>$OBEVO_HOME/bin/deploy.sh -dir /home/myuser/myproject/latest-version/db -env prod</li>
                <li>Extra features like cleaning and rebuilding existing schemas and detecting/firing reorgs</li>
            </ul></section>
        <section name="How to read this doc">
        <ul>
            <li>Sections 1-6 are intro information</li>
            <li>Section 7 is how to onboard an {+}{+}<i>existing</i> system; (for new systems, sections 1-6
                would suffice)
            </li>
            <li>Sections 8-onward are advanced use cases</li>
        </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Document Conventions">
        <p>This documentation assumes we are running this from a Windows desktop. Adjust the command line arguments accordingly for Linux if you choose</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>