<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2017 Goldman Sachs.
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.

-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Onboarding Guide - Choosing a Strategy for your System</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <macro name="toc">
            <param name="fromDepth" value="0" />
            <param name="toDepth" value="1" />
        </macro>
        <section name="Onboarding Guide - Choosing a Strategy for your System">
            <p>Once you've familiarized yourself with DeployAnywhere via the documentation or kata, how do you then apply
                this to your actual system (i.e. to apply to your dev/qa/prod environments)?
            </p>

            <p>Keep in mind the end goal of onboarding your schema, which is to be able to:
                <ol>
                    <li>Deploy incremental changes to your uat/production environments</li>
                    <li>Deploy a full schema to a blank environment for testing</li>
                    <li>Maintain all DB objects in your source code and match all the shards in your
                        Production environment. By shards, we mean if your production environment has multiple instances,
                        e.g. a host per region
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>

            <p>Depending on the characteristics of your system, you have different routes to take to this end state.</p>

            <p>See the table below for what you should take for your system.</p>

            <table>
                <tr>
                    <th>Strategy</th>
                    <th>Available Features</th>
                    <th>Applicability to your system</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="new-onboarding-guide.html">New Systems</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>All</td>
                    <td>1) If you have not deployed any DB objects to your Production environment, or you can wipe away your
                        production database and start clean
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="existing-onboarding-guide.html">Existing Systems - Single/Matching Shards</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>All</td>
                    <td>1) If you have DB objects already in your Production environment that should not be touched when
                        onboarding to DeployAnywhere
                        <br />
                        2) All your production DB shards match in schema, or are easily reconcilable (* - see below for more)
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="existing-diverging-onboarding-guide.html">Existing Systems - Diverging Shards</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>All</td>
                    <td>1) If you have DB objects already in your Production environment that should not be touched when
                        onboarding to DeployAnywhere
                        <br />
                        2) You have multiple production DB shards that do not match easily, but you would like to maintain them as one code-base
                        and possibly unify them over time. (* - see below for more)
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="legacy-onboarding-guide.html">Legacy Systems (not recommended - only exceptional cases)</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>#1 - only to deploy to uat/prod environments</td>
                    <td>1) If you have DB objects already in your Production environment that should not be touched when
                        onboarding to DeployAnywhere
                        <br />
                        2) You have multiple production DB shards that do not match easily
                        <br />
                        3) If you have a legacy system about to be retired for which you don't want/need the investment for
                        the testing features, but need to get by with production deployments until the system is retired.
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>


        <section name="(*) Guidance on the Matching vs. Diverging Shards condition for Existing Systems">
            <p>Clarifying the point on matching shards - for DB object maintenance, ideally the following condition should hold:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <b>
                            <i>Each DB object should have the same definition in all production DB shards</i>
                        </b>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <p>Use cases where this is achieved:
                <ol>
                    <li>If you have 1 production shard (trivial)</li>
                    <li>If you have multiple production shards that have always been maintained in sync, e.g. if you had proper
                        and design over your database migrations.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>

            <p>However, some systems may not be in this ideal state for various reasons, e.g. a long-lived system that
                was built and evolved before DB SDLC practices came into vogue, with various functional system enhancements
                causing the schemas to diverge.
            </p>

            <p>If this matches your case, you have a few questions to ask:
                <ol>
                    <li>Is the same application code modifying all instances? Do you truly care about having a single
                        canonical copy of DDLs across your production instances?
                        <ul>
                            <li>If not, then simply maintain separate for each (i.e. a Single-shard Existing System
                                Onboarding for each production shard.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>If so, then you should into the<a
                        href="existing-diverging-onboarding-guide.html">Diverging Shards Onboarding Guide</a>,
                        which gives you guidance on how to get your diverging shard schemas into source control, then to
                        evolve/fix the divergent objects over time into a unified model (if you choose to merge them).
                    </li>
                    <li>Last-resort - if your system is being retired soon and you want to save the merge work at a cost
                        of features, then use the
                        <a href="legacy-onboarding-guide.html">Legacy Onboarding Strategy</a>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section
            name="FAQ: Can I onboard only a subset of my existing DB objects initially, and then incrementally onboard more later?">
            <p>Short Answer: No</p>

            <p>Long Answer: No, because it will:
                <ul>
                    <li>Save significant amounts of time long term (and possibly even short term) compared to incremental onboarding</li>
                    <li>Significantly reduce short-term and long-term risk over your database changes</li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            It is our explicit design choice and recommendation (as opposed
            to a technical limitation).

            <p>We recognize the difficulty of managing an existing production systems and the aversion to change. Some
                reasons we have heard on wanting to onboard objects incrementally:
                <ul>
                    <li>1) Too many objects in production, a lot of effort to onboard them all</li>
                    <li>2) Many objects that we don't know about or that haven't been touched in a while; why bother with onboarding them</li>
                    <li>3) Multiple teams deploy to that schema; we want to onboard our changes without impacting them</li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <p>We can address these points:</p>

            <h3>1) Handling large schemas</h3>
            <p>We have onboarded many
                <b>
                    <i>LARGE</i>
                </b>
                schemas (i.e. reverse-engineer from production and get a working
                copy deployed to a test schema
                <ul>800 tables, 5000 SPs, 200 views in Sybase ASE</ul>
                <ul>700 tables, 1000 SPs, 80 functions, 200 views in DB2</ul>
                <ul>200 tables, 100 SPs, 250 user types (!), 1 DEFAULT in Sybase ASE</ul>
                <ul>... and so on</ul>
                <ul>... with a lot of complexity (interdependencies among SPs, from functions to tables back to functions, ...)</ul>
            </p>

            <p>Onboarding each schemas has taken
                <i>
                    <u>2 days in the worst-case</u>
                </i>
                .
            </p>

            <p>We've invested a lot in our onboarding tooling to make it easier. In fact, much of the time in this
                onboarding is really to clean up "invalid objects" , i.e. objects that refer to no-longer-existing objects.
                If your schema is clean, onboarding is no issue. And we've enhanced our onboarding workflow to make it
                easier to see and resolve issues.
            </p>

            <p>Hence, regardless of the difficulty that you expect when onboarding, you can be assured that we have seen
                many other difficult use cases in the past and that our tooling will be up to the challenge. And if you
                have a use case that our tool hasn't seen yet, you will have some eager folks ready to improve the tool
                to solve your issue! (as we have done with many others in the past)
            </p>

            <h3>2) Cost of not onboarding upfront</h3>

            <p>As mentioned in #1, we make it easy to onboard your objects. But is there any harm in not deploying all
                objects regardless? Yes, we can name two
            </p>

            <p>A) You have not changed these objects recently in the past...that doesn't mean they won't change in the future</p>

            <p>B) You many really only care about a single table or SP or view. But you may find that it depends
                on another view or SP, which means you have to redo the onboarding steps for those objects. And
                <i>those</i>
                may depend on yet another view or SP or table, which means you have to redo the onboarding steps...you
                get the idea.
            </p>

            <p>It could end up much simpler and less costly to then do the full onboarding.</p>

            <h3>3) Better for all owners of a schema to onboard than a single owner at a time</h3>

            <p>In some older systems, multiple teams may be performing deployments against a single schema or want to
                maintain their objects separately. It is understandable that one team may want to onboard without affecting
                the other teams. However, this can lead to some complexities:
            </p>

            <p>A) As mentioned in #2B, you may not know upfront if your subset of objects is truly independent, or if
                there is some dependency on another group's objects, or vice versa.
            </p>

            <p>B) Having visibility on all changes going into a schema would reduce risks for all teams. Would teams not
                worry about any migrations from other teams that would potentially affect their own? Onboarding all the
                objects in that schema would at least make it easier to keep tabs on what other teams are doing.
            </p>

            <p>That said - teams still would have options on keeping their DDLs separate if they choose (even if the
                deployment is ultimately done from a single source). See the FAQ for more information
            </p>

            <h3>Summary - go with onboarding a full schema</h3>
            <p>No tooling is perfect, especially for cleaning up tough situations like long-lived schemas. But given our
                experience with this in the past and our investment into the onboarding tooling, we strongly feel the
                full schema onboarding is the way to go. Feel free to give us feedback if you have any difficulties
                onboarding your use case.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>