<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2017 Goldman Sachs.
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.

-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Rollback</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <p>What should you consider when rolling back? Read on for the various options.</p>

        <hr />

        <macro name="toc">
            <param name="fromDepth" value="0" />
            <param name="toDepth" value="2" />
        </macro>

        <section name="Roll-back / roll-forward considerations during or after DB deployment">
            <p>This section describes actions you would take to handle issues that prevent you from otherwise proceeding
                (or planning ahead for such cases). The main use cases:
                <ol>
                    <li>UC1: Issues during a deployment execution (i.e. the previous section)</li>
                    <li>UC2: Issues during application execution after a successful DB deployment, or for planning ahead for
                        such cases (e.g. rollback preparation)
                    </li>
                    <ul>
                        <li>i.e. in case the DB deployment succeeds, and the application rollout does not, you have two choices
                            with your application: roll-forward or roll-back. Roll-forward should imply that your database changes
                            can remain. What about rolling the application back - what then with your DB code?
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </ol>
            </p>

            <p>The following are various paradigms to follow to handle or plan for these situations. We list these out
                in priority order:
            </p>
            <ol>
                <li>(Most favored) Avoiding rollbacks using backwards-compatible changes</li>
                <li>Rolling forward, i.e. executing new changes to rollback</li>
                <li>Backing up the whole DB (e.g. dbdump and restore)</li>
                <li>(Least favored) Traditional rollback, i.e. preparing rollback scripts alongside your release</li>
            </ol>

            <p>You may ultimately need to consider all options; e.g. you may always write backwards-compatible changes,
                but you may still need to roll forward in some cases.
            </p>

            <p>More details on each section:</p>


            <subsection name="Paradigm 1: Avoiding rollbacks using backwards-compatible changes">
                <p>(Only applicable for UC2)</p>

                <p>If it were easy to put your database back into its previous state, then great. Most often, it is not
                    the case, as tables are stateful objects. For example, adding and then removing table columns would mean
                    physically changing all the rows in the database, which can be an expensive operation. Not to mention
                    that such a rollback operation should also be tested.
                </p>

                <p>What is an easier way to roll back your DB changes then? How about...not rolling them back at all?</p>

                <p>Making your DB schema changes backwards-compatible to your code would help in this regard. The DB
                    migration can only be done once and not worried about again, as this is a relatively more expensive
                    operation than app binary updates.
                </p>

                <p>Some teams have taken it as far as
                    <i>
                        <u>releasing DB code changes far in advance of application
                            code changes
                        </u>
                    </i>
                    as to prove backwards compatibility.
                </p>

                <p>Some general rules on what changes are/aren't backwards-compatible:
                    <ul>
                        <li>Backwards-compatible: adding a nullable column</li>
                        <li>NOT Backwards-compatible: adding a non-nullable column</li>
                        <li>NOT Backwards-compatible: removing a column in use in production today</li>
                        <li>Backwards-compatible: removing a column that is not used in production code and has no risk
                            of being used due to rollback
                        </li>
                        <li>Risk of NOT Backwards-compatible: stored procedure or view changes; treat this as you would
                            treat code in terms of attempting to preserve backwards-compatibility
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                    More notes here on
                    <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/evodb.html">Martin Fowler's page</a>
                    (search for references to "destructive chagnes")
                </p>

                <p>However, you may not be able to escape such non-backwards-compatible changes; or you may choose not
                    choose for the overhead of backwards-compatible changes. Then choose from the next possible options.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Paradigm 2: Rolling forward, i.e. executing new changes to rollback">
                <p>Instead of preparing to rollback, you may instead choose to release a new patch version to fix the
                    issue with your release. The patch can be either in your application code or in your database code.
                </p>

                <p>A risk here is that you do not have your changes pre-planned, and so if an issue comes up, you would
                    need to come up w/ a solution on the fly. However, depending on your application characteristics (well-tested,
                    nimble for making and deploying changes, able to cope with the bug for long enough), this can be suitable
                    for you as this saves the overhead of planning out backwards-compatible changes or rollback scripts.
                </p>

                <p>To roll forward, treat this change much as you would treat a patch release, e.g.</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Check out your prod tag/branch that has these DB changes</li>
                    <li>Add a new //// CHANGE to the file to undo the impact of the change that you added</li>
                    <li>Commit your code</li>
                    <li>Execute the deploy...</li>
                </ul>
                <p>... For executing the deploy, you have options:</p>
                <ol>
                    <li>You can always go through the standard deployment process to release this change (i.e. much as
                        you would for an application code change). This is the preferred approach
                    </li>
                    <li>Or you may feel you can't wait for the build to go through. In that case, you can just call
                        DeployAnywhere locally against your checked-out code. (It is just Java after all; it can execute
                        anywhere. But ensure that your code is committed)
                        <ul>
                            <li>However, from an SDLC perspective, this is not recommended. Please try to abide by your
                            team's/firm's build and release practices.</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Paradigm 3: Backing up the whole DB (e.g. dbdump and restore)">
                <p>Ultimately, the purest form of rollback would be to take a raw copy of the DB before doing the
                    deployment,
                    and then switching back to it if the code also needs to get rolled back.
                </p>
                <p>Some DBMSs (e.g. Sybase ASE) do provide such tooling for this (e.g. dbdump and restore). Thus, you
                    can resort
                    to this mode of rollback if you choose (likely, your DBAs should be taking backups of your DB
                    anyway). As
                    the DeployAnywhere audit table is also physically on your target DB, the state of the audit table
                    will also
                    get rolled back to where it should be.
                </p>
                <p>The main negative with this approach is if your DB is huge, then this process will take a while to
                    run and
                    requires a lot of disk storage in your infrastructure. Hence, most teams will not go with this for
                    practical
                    reasons, but certainly if you have the resources and time for it, this is an acceptable option.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Paradigm 4: Traditional rollback, i.e. preparing rollback scripts alongside your release">
                DeployAnywhere supports rollback by simply allowing developers to point to their old DB package and
                re-deploy w/ the \-rollback flag attached

                For example:
                <source><![CDATA[# do the deployment of version 1
$DEPLOYANY_HOME/bin/deploy.bat DEPLOY -env prod -sourcePath /home/myuser/mypackage/1.0.0/db

# do the deployment of version 2 (which contains rollback scripts if needed)
$DEPLOYANY_HOME/bin/deploy.bat DEPLOY -env prod -sourcePath /home/myuser/mypackage/2.0.0/db

# let's say that goes bad; we'll rollback to version 1 by deploying it w/ the -rollback tag
$DEPLOYANY_HOME/bin/deploy.bat DEPLOY -env prod -sourcePath /home/myuser/mypackage/1.0.0/db
-rollback]]></source>

                <p>In the example above, the changes in version 2 need to include the rollback scripts.</p>
                <p>In terms of what roll providing the scripts:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>For stateless objects (i.e. everything except &quot;table&quot; changes): nothing extra is
                        needed.
                        DeployAnywhere simply detects the objects in the old location and applies those (doing the
                        appropriate
                        drops and adds as necessary)
                    </li>
                    <li>For tables:
                        <ul>
                            <li>If you don't want to add a rollback script for a particular //// CHANGE, nothing extra
                                is
                                needed. DeployAnywhere will simply let the change remain.
                            </li>
                            <li>If you do want a rollback script for a particular //// CHANGE, add a // ROLLBACK
                                subsection to
                                the change in question. See the example below, note the &quot;chng-from-2.0.0&quot;
                                CHANGE
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <source><![CDATA[//// CHANGE name=chng-from-1.0.0
CREATE TABLE TABLE_A (
    A_ID INT NOT NULL,
    B_ID INT NOT NULL,
    STRING_FIELD VARCHAR(30) NULL,
    TIMESTAMP_FIELD TIMESTAMP NULL,
    PRIMARY KEY (A_ID)
)
GO
//// CHANGE name=chng-from-2.0.0
ALTER TABLE TABLE_A ADD COLUMN C_ID INT NULL
GO
// ROLLBACK
ALTER TABLE TABLE_A DROP COLUMN C_ID
GO]]></source>
                <p>In case you are interested in the technical details behind this: {panel}First, let's review how
                    regular deployments are done and changes detect (see <a href="design-walkthrough.html">Design Walkthrough</a> doc)
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>For stateless objects (sp, view, ...): when we detect a change between the source code and what
                        was
                        deployed in the db (whether a change in the file, a creation of a new file, or a deletion/drop
                        of the
                        file), we simply detect it and apply the change.
                    </li>
                    <li>For stateful objects (tables): table changes are detected as new //// CHANGE entries in the
                        file. And we
                        are not allowed to drop or modify any previously-deployed changes
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <p>Now for rollback:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>For stateless objects, we have no problem, as going from v2.0.0 to v1.0.0. is just created as
                        another
                        deployment change, and so we'd deploy whatever changes we'd get when going from 2.0.0 to 1.0.0
                    </li>
                    <li>For tables, we will typically get a case where the tool detects that we've improperly removed a
                        change
                        from the file that has been deployed already. The -rollback flag handles this by:
                        <ul>
                            <li>Will not fail the deployment if some exception like this is detected</li>
                            <li>For each deployed change, we have the option of specifying a // ROLLBACK command (see
                                below).
                                This will only get activated if we execute -rollback and we have a case where a change
                                deployed
                                as part of 2.0.0 is no longer there in 1.0.0
                            </li>
                            <li>Fyi, this -ROLLBACK script is stored in the audit table. This is because it is v2.0.0's
                                changes
                                that we are rolling back, and if we rollback by pointing to the old version, then we'd
                                have no
                                place to get the rollback script from. Hence, we store it in the db{panel}
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <p>Note that if you execute this rollback command, it will still ultimately remain in your source code
                    to be
                    deployed in subsequent releases and in the UAT environments that you deployed to. If you want to
                    remove this
                    change entirely (i.e. not let it come back in the next release), see the section below for &quot;(Special
                    Case) Undoing a table/incremental change permanently in non-prod or after rollback&quot;</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Anti-Pattern Paradigm: Backing up individual tables before deployment">
                <p>This involves creating a backup of the table during your deployment (e.g. MY<i>TABLE</i>BAK20141017),
                    copying
                    the data over, and proceeding w/ the deployment.
                </p>
                <p>Pros:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Preserves your data, particularly for complex migrations that you do Cons:</li>
                    <li>Takes time and space to copy the data over (not as efficient in runtime as a db copy, as
                        ultimately this
                        needs to be expressed a SQL)
                    </li>
                    <li>Requires some coding to perform, incl. the sqls to copy the data over and to rerun stats after
                        rolling
                        back (if we do end up rolling back)
                    </li>
                    <li>Need to remember to clean up the tables after the fact</li>
                </ul>
                <p>While certainly we can add tooling around this to support this use case, most teams can get by using
                    the
                    others listed earlier. Hence, we haven't built anything to support this paradigm as of yet
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Roll-back / roll-forward considerations for non-prod deployments">
            <p>The above scenarios are what you should do if you are rolling back a change in production.</p>
            <p>However, in non-prod (e.g. qa/uat), you still have cases where you want to undo a change you had
                applied
                during your current version. For undoing table changes, this would mean adding another //// CHANGE
                entry
                (assuming you can't just wipe away and clean your db)
            </p>
            <p>But if you are in qa/uat, you may have a lot of these changes building up if you have a lot of
                corrections.
                What if you want to be able to undo the change in uat and be able to delete the change entry in your
                file
                too? (As discussed a few times earlier, you cannot simply delete a //// CHANGE entry as the tool
                catches
                that as a validation error)
            </p>
            <p>To do that, you can add the ROLLBACK-IF-ALREADY-DEPLOYED subsection to your change, e.g.</p>
            <source><![CDATA[//// CHANGE name=chng-from-1.0.0
CREATE TABLE TABLE_A (
    A_ID INT NOT NULL,
    B_ID INT NOT NULL,
    STRING_FIELD VARCHAR(30) NULL,
    TIMESTAMP_FIELD TIMESTAMP NULL,
    PRIMARY KEY (A_ID)
)
GO
//// CHANGE name=uat-change
ALTER TABLE TABLE_A ADD COLUMN C_ID INT NULL
GO
// ROLLBACK-IF-ALREADY-DEPLOYED
ALTER TABLE TABLE_A DROP COLUMN C_ID
GO]]></source>
            <p>The way this will work:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>If the tool sees that &quot;uat-change&quot; had &quot;NOT&quot; been deployed and it sees the
                    presence
                    of a ROLLBACK-IF-ALREADY-DEPLOYED section, then it will simply ignore the change
                </li>
                <li>If the tool sees that &quot;uat-change&quot; had already been deployed and it sees the presence
                    of a
                    ROLLBACK-IF-ALREADY-DEPLOYED section, then it will execute the rollback and remove the change
                    name from
                    the deployment audit table. Thus, once you've wiped this out from all environments, you can
                    delete this
                    section from your file
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>